Raluca-Maria Sandu

RESEARCHER · DATA SCIENTIST

▼raluca.sandu@rwth-aachen.de | ★rmsandu.github.io | ☑rmsandu | 匝rmsandu



About Me

I am a perseverant and resourceful scientific professional who just finished their PhD Degree in Biomedical Engineering at the University of Bern, previously having graduated with an MSc in the same field, and a BSc in Control Engineering and Applied Computer Science. I am specialized in working on data science and research & development projects across various topics as evidenced by my work experience and studies.

Work Experience __

University of Bern, ARTORG Center for Biomedical Engineering Research

Bern, Switzerland

DOCTORAL CANDIDATE (PHD)

May 2017 - Feb. 2021

- Worked with data mining, image processing & registration, radiomics & feature extraction, statistics, and machine learning algorithms in the area of CT-guided ablation treatments for liver cancer by using Python and R programming languages.
- Developed a quantitative and numerical evaluation method based on DICOM image segmentations for assessing the success of liver ablation treatments which was published in a peer-reviewed journal. More info **here**.

Philips Research, Personal Care and Wellness

Eindhoven, The Netherlands

Jul. 2016 - Mar. 2017

- RESEARCH AND DEVELOPMENT GRADUATE STUDENT
- Designed and developed a web-based application for image annotation using JavaScript, HTML and CSS that can be found **here**.
- $\bullet \ \ \, \text{Applied image processing and machine learning algorithms in Python (SVM, PCA, Random Forests)} for classification of skin surface structures.$

Philips Research, Personal Care and Wellness

Eindhoven, The Netherlands

RESEARCH AND DEVELOPMENT INTERNSHIP

Apr. 2016 - Jun. 2016

• Contributed with exploratory 2D image analysis in Python to quantify the effect of various diets on physical appearance at skin surface.

RWTH Aachen, Joint Research Centre for Computational Biomedicine

Aachen, Germany

STUDENT RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Nov. 2014 - Jul. 2015

• Carried out exploratory data analysis in MATLAB to study interactions between cancer cell lines.

Philips Research, Personal Health

Eindhoven, The Netherlands

RESEARCH AND DEVELOPMENT INTERNSHIP

Jul. 2013 - Oct. 2013

• Explored in MATLAB the feasibility of a device to diagnose lung diseases by employing signal processing and machine learning algorithms.

Philips Research, Personal Health

Eindhoven, The Netherlands

RESEARCH AND DEVELOPMENT INTERNSHIP

Jul. 2012 - Sep. 2012

• Implemented data mining and statistics in MATLAB to analyze the physiological signals of chronic heart failure patients.

Education

University of Bern, ARTORG Center for Biomedical Engineering Research

Bern, Switzerland

PHD IN BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING

May 2017 - Feb. 2021

- Thesis: "Quantitative assessment of ablation treatments for liver tumours image-based efficacy analysis and predictive modelling".
- PhD project part of a Marie Skłodowska-Curie ITN grant aimed at improving soft tissue clinical treatments.
- Thesis supervisor: Prof. Dr. Raphael Sznitman.

RWTH Aachen University, Faculty of Medicine

Aachen, Germany

MSc in Biomedical Engineering

Oct. 2014 - Apr. 2017

- Thesis: "Image Segmentation and Semantic Description: Tools and Analytics" carried out at Philips Research Eindhoven.
- Thesis Project Grade: 100%. GPA: 83%.

Politehnica University of Bucharest, Faculty of Automatic Control and Computers

Bucharest, Romania

BSC IN CONTROL ENGINEERING AND APPLIED COMPUTER SCIENCE

Oct. 2010 - Jul. 2014

- Thesis: "Volumetric Capnography Respiratory Signals for Spontaneously Breathing Subjects" carried out at Philips Research Eindhoven.
- Thesis Project Grade: 98%. GPA: 83%.

IT& Technical Skills

Python. Numpy, scikit-learn, scipy, pydicom, pyradiomics, simpleitk, pandas, opency, matplotlib, seaborn. Strong

Machine Learning. PCA, SVM, decision trees, random forests, k-means, regression, cross-validation, ROC, F-score.

Version Control. Git, GitHub, Bitbucket (Jira + Confluence), Sourcetree.

Knowledgeable **Deep Learning.** TensorFlow, PyTorch, Keras (Coursera and Udemy Studies).

R Programming. Statistics and data manipulation: Ismeans, Ime4, ggplot2, tidyverse.

MATLAB. Data, signal and image processing. **C/C++/C#.** Object-Oriented Programming (OOP).

Database Design. SQL, ER model, normalisation. MySQL, PostgreSQL, PHP.

Web Design. Django, JavaScript, HTML, CSS, JSON, Markdown, Hugo.

Languages _

C1 English. Certificate in Advanced English (CAE), University of Cambridge ESOL, Grade A (100%) (2009).

B2 German. Completed B2.2. German Language Course at University of Bern (2017-2019).

В1 French. Diplôme d'études en langue française DELF B1, Grade 80% (2009).

Extracurricular Activities

Volunteering

Vice-President at IAESTE. Organizing local events for visiting interns and promoting available internships and workshops.

Hobbies Skiing, Snowboarding, Hiking, Surfing, Yoga, Painting.

Publications

Peer-Reviewed Articles

Volumetric Quantitative Ablation Margins for Assessment of Ablation Completeness in Thermal Ablation of Liver Tumours R.-M. Sandu, I. Paolucci, S. J. S. Ruiter, R. Sznitman, K. P. de Jong, J. Freedman, S. Weber, and P. Tinguely Frontiers in Oncology, vol. 11, 2021

DOI: 10.3389/fonc.2021.623098

Accuracy of Electrode Placement in IRE Treatment with Navigated Guidance

D. Stillström, R.-M. Sandu, and J. Freedman

CardioVascular and Interventional Radiology 2021

DOI: 10.1007/s00270-020-02762-5

Ultrasound based planning and navigation for non anatomical liver resections — an ex-vivo study I. Paolucci, R.-M. Sandu, L. Sahli, G. A. Prevost, F. Storni, D. Candinas, S. Weber, and A. Lachenmayer

IEEE Open Journal of Engineering in Medicine and Biology, 2019

DOI: 10.1109/0JEMB.2019.2961094

Conference Proceedings

Quantitative volumetric assessment of percutaneous image-guided microwave ablations for colorectal liver metastases R.-M. Sandu, I. Paolucci, J. Freedman, P. Tinguely, S. J. S. Ruiter, and S. Weber 31st Conference of the International Society for Medical Innovation and Technology (iSMIT), 2019, Heilbronn, Germany

Quantitative Volumetric Assessment of CT-guided Ablation Treatments for Colorectal Liver Metastases [2] R.-M. Sandu, I. Paolucci, J. Freedman, P. Tinguely, and S. Weber

IEEE Engineering in Medicine and Biology Society (EMBS) International Student Conference (ISC), 2019, Magdeburg, Germany

Quantitative volumetric assessment of percutaneous image-guided microwave ablations for colorectal liver metastases R.-M. Sandu, I. Paolucci, J. Freedman, and S. Weber

CURAC, 18th Annual Meeting of the German Society for Computer and Robot-Assisted Surgery, 2019, Reutligen, Germany

Book Chapter

Stereotactic Image-Guidance for Ablation of Malignant Liver Tumors

I. Paolucci, R.-M. Sandu, P. Tinguely, C. Kim-Fuchs, M. Maurer, D. Candinas, S. Weber, and A. Lachenmayer

Liver Cancer, 2019

DOI: 10.5772/intechopen.89722

References

Available upon request.